Guide to the Robert Averill Walker Papers SC0546
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert Averill Walker papers
1950-1995
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Walker, Robert Averill
SC0546
21.75 Linear Feet
Papers pertain largely to his administrative duties at Stanford University and include correspondence, minutes, agenda, memoranda, and reports; subjects include the overseas studies program, the political science department, international studies, curriculum reviews, and faculty/staff housing on campus. Also of note are the minutes with indexes from the Committee on University Policy, 1959-68, and the Advisory Committee on Land and Building Development, 1951-57. Collection also includes photograph albums and slides of the Stanford overseas campuses and/or programs in Britain, France, Germany, Italy, Austria, and Japan.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of the estate of Robert A. Walker, 1998.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Robert A. Walker was a professor of political science whose specialty was public administration and urban planning, Walker was also tapped by former President Wallace Sterling and Provost Frederick Terman to help draft land use plans for Stanford-owned open space surrounding the campus. As a member of the university's committee on land and buildings from 1952 to 1969, he helped write plans for Stanford Industrial Park and as chair of the committee on faculty-staff housing, he oversaw the development of three faculty housing subdivisions: Pine Hill I and II and Frenchman's Hill. He also prided himself as being among those who fought a winning battle for maintaining the campus architectural tradition of sloped red tile roofs at a time when architects proposed less expensive flat tops.
A generation of students knew him best, however, for the "green sheet," an extensive list of required courses outside their majors, which he ushered in as director of general studies in 1956, and as the man who made possible their first experiences abroad.
Aided by the strength of the American dollar, Walker leased whole airplanes to take Stanford undergraduates to overseas campuses that he and Professor Friedrich Strothmann started in 1958, first in Germany, and then in France, Italy, Austria, Great Britain and Spain. At a time when other universities were sending a few exceptional students to study in foreign universities, Walker wanted to expose as many as possible to other cultures, believing that an international perspective was an essential part of a liberal education. Three of every five Stanford undergraduates, 8,000 in all, went abroad for two quarters during his tenure as director of overseas campus programs, which ended in 1973. With so many students away, the university also was able to increase its total enrollment.
"I grew up on a farm near Phoenix. When I got to Austria, I was so excited about seeing the place that I could scarcely think about doing work," recalls Lowell Price, A.B. '66, currently secretary to the Stanford Board of Trustees. "I think that's why we got a reputation for being on a travel lark," said Price, who, like many other students, met his future spouse, a fellow Stanford student, abroad.
"For his time, Bob Walker was a tremendous innovator," Price said, conceding he would not be so pleased today if his own children spent as much time away from the books as he did in Europe. (The overseas program, which will celebrate its 40th anniversary this year, has since been given a more rigorous academic focus and expanded to Asia and Latin America.) Walker also used the European campuses to try out co-educational housing at a time when university officials carefully kept male and female students housed across campus, said Price, who later worked for Walker. He also developed small group learning experiences, by recruiting faculty to travel abroad, teaching and living with the students in the host countries long before the university began encouraging faculty mentors to live in student residence halls.
Not all went smoothly, however, according to one of Walker's sons, who also took advantage of the overseas experience. "Some students sat around and moaned about having to eat sauerkraut and wurst in Germany," said his son Jerome, A.B. '65 and Ph.D. '72, now associate provost at the University of Southern California. "My father's philosophy was that we weren't about to take American food to Europe."
In a 1971 publication for students, the senior Walker warned that "some students are so provincial that they live in nearly private cocoons which quite successfully insulate them from new experiences abroad."
Walker's ideas about a liberal education included reading the "Great Books" and were derived from educational philosopher Robert Maynard Hutchins, who was president of the University of Chicago when Walker and his wife, Louise, were students there. They became lifelong converts to the classics and belonged to a Stanford faculty group that regularly met to read parts in plays in the late '40s. Walker introduced a liberal curriculum at Kansas State, where he headed the "Institute of Citizenship." At Stanford, he chaired a 1955-56 committee on undergraduate education, which developed the first plan for undergraduate studies at Stanford in 40 years. The curricular reforms lasted until the late '60s when the university undertook another major study and revision.
Born Jan. 11, 1914, in Spokane, Wash., Walker earned bachelor's and doctoral degrees from Chicago. In 1937 he and his wife drove across country gathering interviews with city mayors and planners for his doctoral thesis on urban land use planning, Jerome Walker said. "They had to choose between buying a radio or a heater for the car. They chose a radio and my mother always regretted it."
In 1939, Walker joined the National Resources Planning Board, where he got into trouble with a supervisor over his yet-to-be-published thesis, which eventually became a textbook on urban planning. Walker had argued that city planning boards had become overly dominated by real estate and construction industry interests, and his supervisor wanted him to modify his conclusions, Walker later told his son. "Dad wouldn't change it, so he had to leave, but his professors at Chicago found him a research fellowship," Jerome said.
Walker then worked in administrative positions for the Departments of Agriculture and State before becoming a professor at Kansas State. He came to Stanford in 1949, when the regional university was setting its sights on developing a national reputation.
"He took over as chair of the political science department [in 1958] at a time when it had less than 10 faculty members, and it wasn't number one in quality of political science either," recalls Kurt Steiner, a professor emeritus of political science who earned his doctorate at Stanford in 1955. "He brought in people such as Heinz Eulau and other luminaries that finally brought the department onto the national map."
Walker wrote or co-authored several books, including one about California governance in 1953, and taught courses on public administration until his retirement in 1976. "He was a New Deal Roosevelt Democrat who believed in the enlightened civil servant who would run government for you," said his son Richard, A.B. '69, now chair of the geography department at the University of California-Berkeley.
Working closely with Sterling and Terman, Steiner said, Walker was known more among Stanford political scientists as an administrator with hands-on experience than as a researcher or theoretician. "In a field like politics, a little practical experience connected with a sound academic background is a useful thing," Steiner said, "but I remember when he retired I gave a talk in which I said he wasn't very popular in our department because he tried to put administrative principles to work. There was a certain resentment that, as chair, he tried to really administer at a time when most chairs didn't do too much."
Within overseas studies, however, his administrative skills were more appreciated, said Giuseppe Mammarella, an Italian political scientist who was the first director of Stanford's Florence campus. "Bob found the [foreign campus] sites, negotiated the contracts, designed the programs in close contact with the departments at home," Mammarella said, and was known for his enthusiasm and endurance " After several hours of discussion, there was only one person around the conference table who was as fresh as a rose, smiling and bursting with optimism: Bob Walker," Mammarella said.
History Professor Mark Mancall, who took over as director of overseas studies from Walker in 1973, said that he "played a major role in developing the concept of general studies at Stanford and in integrating international education through overseas studies" into the curriculum. "He also was extraordinarily helpful and cooperative in various transitions" in the programs, he said.
Walker is survived by his wife, Louise, of Stanford; brother Tom of Pittsburgh; sons Jerome of Los Angeles, Robert of Stanford and Richard of Berkeley; and four grandchildren. Family services will be held Monday morning, Feb. 9, at Alta Mesa Cemetery. A memorial service is planned for Stanford's Memorial Church at 3:30 p.m. on Monday, March 16.
By Kathleen O'Toole, Stanford University News Service
Description of the Collection
Papers pertain largely to his administrative duties at Stanford University and include correspondence, minutes, agenda, memoranda, and reports; subjects include the overseas studies program, the political science department, international studies, curriculum reviews, and faculty/staff housing on campus. Also of note are the minutes with indexes from the Committee on University Policy, 1959-68, and the Advisory Committee on Land and Building Development, 1951-57. Collection also includes photograph albums and slides of the Stanford overseas campuses and/or programs in Britain, France, Germany, Italy, Austria, and Japan.
Foreign study.; Slides.; Universities and colleges -- Curricula.; Universities and colleges -- Administration.; Photoprints.; Stanford University. Department of Political Science; Stanford University. Committee on International Studies; Walker, Robert Averill; Walker, Robert Averill; Stanford University. Overseas Study Program
- Original Accession, Accession ARCH-1998-097
  - Basic documents, general, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Basic and historical documents, overseas campuses, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Basic and historical documents, overseas campuses, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Basic and historical documents, overseas campuses, 1968 December - 1970 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Basic and historical documents, overseas campuses, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Land & Building Committee - distribution and membership (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Land & Building Committee - general, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Land & Building Committee - general, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Land & Building Committee - general, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - distribution and membership (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - general, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - general, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - governance committee report (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - governance subcom. incl. annexation (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - residents' letters re annexation, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - ground rent, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - Hanna committee on apartments (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - emeriti, senior staff, and junior faculty housing (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - on-campus loans, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - Searvsville Lake (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing -low income housing general, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - low income housing, residents' letters (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - low income housing, Veinott report (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - low income housing, Wright report (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - 1967 questionnaire re multiple housing (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Faculty/Staff Housing - pre-school park, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Faculty Housing announcement of subdivisions, maps (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Faculty Housing future agenda (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1966 April - 1967 June (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1967 July - 1968 August (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Housing general, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Housing Frenchmen's Road letters (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Foster - honor's thesis (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bancroft - honor's thesis (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rumpf - urban studies (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - U.S. Civil Service Commission - recruitment (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ford Foundation Proposal by R. A. Walker (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Liquor policy (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Residence policies, 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Comm ittee on Undergraduate Education, general, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Political Science Dept. Research in Public Affairs Committee (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Political Science Dept. Graham Stuart Fund (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Political Science Dept. International Relations (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Political Science Dept. International Relations Inventory (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Political Science Dept. National Center for Educ. in Politics (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Political Science Dept. NIPA [National Institute of Public Affairs] financial (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Political Science Dept. NIP A general, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Political Science Dept. Appointments and Promotions (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Political Science Dept. Comparative Administration (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Political Science Dept. CA Legislative Internship Program (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Political Science Dept. Coro Foundation (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Political Science Dept. Cottrell Fund (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Political Science Dept. Professor Walker. Administrative Memoranda, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Political Science Dept. Minutes of Dept., meetings, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Political Science Dept. Graduate Study Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Political Science Dept. Graduate Study Committee, 1968-1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Political Science Dept. Graduate Study Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, Solicitation and Responses, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, prior to 1961, circa 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, Theory, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Political Science Dept. Search Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Political Science Dept. General, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Robert A. Walker. British Subcom. Minutes (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Robert A. Walker. Austria Subcom. Minutes (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP. Minutes, 1970 January - 1972 June (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP. Minutes, 1972 September - 1973 April (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Robert A. Walker. French Subcom. Minutes (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Robert A. Walker. German Subcom. Minutes (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Robert A. Walker. Italian Subcom. Minutes (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Robert A. Walker. Presidential Commission. General (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Robert A. Walker. Presidential Commission. Comments on report (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Robert A. Walker. Presidential Commission. Responses by faculty and staff (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP. Committee membership (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP Senate Charge and related items (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP general (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Robert A. Walker. Austria Subcom. general (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Robert A. Walker. Austria. Basic documents extra copies (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Robert A. Walker. British subcom. general (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Robert A. Walker. Britain. Basic documents extra copies (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Robert A. Walker. French subcom. general (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Robert A. Walker. France. Basic documents extra copies (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Robert A. Walker. German subcom. general (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Robert A. Walker. Italian subcom. general (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Robert A. Walker. Special programs (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Robert A. Walker. CFSP, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Robert A. Walker. Austria subcom., 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Robert A. Walker. British subcom., 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - RobertA. Walker. Germany, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - RobertA. Walker. Italy, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Carillon [in Hoover Tower] (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Trip correspondence, 1963 Jan. - Feb. (Walker), 1963 January - February (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Trip correspondence, 1963 Jan. (Walker), 1963 January (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Trip correspondence, 1962 Autumn (Irene Blumenthal) (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Trip correspondence, 1962 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Trip correspondence, 1962 Jan. (Blumenthal), 1962 January (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Trip correspondence, 1961 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Trip correspondence, 1964 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Trip correspondence, 1964 Winter (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Trip correspondence, 1963-64 Autumn (Blumenthal), 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Trip correspondence, 1963 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Trip correspondence, 1963 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Trip correspondence, 1966 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Trip correspondence, 1966 April (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Trip correspondence, 1965 Nov. (Walker), 1965 November (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Trip correspondence, 1965 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Trip correspondence, 1965 Mar. - May (Walker), 1965 March - May (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Trip correspondence, 1965 Jan. (Walker), 1965 January (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Trip correspondence, 1968 Spr. (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Trip correspondence, 1967 Nov. (Walker), 1967 November (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Trip correspondence, 1967 Summer (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Trip correspondence, 1967 April (Walker) (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Trip correspondence, 1967 Jan. (Walker), 1967 Janaury (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Trip correspondence, 1966 Nov. (Walker), 1966 November (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Trip correspondence, 1969 Fall (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Trip correspondence, 1969 Summer (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trip correspondence, 1969 March/April (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trip correspondence, 1968 Sept./Oct. (Walker), 1968 September/October (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trip correspondence, 1968 Summer (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Trip correspondence, 1971 Nov. - Dec. (Walker), 1971 November - December (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trip correspondence, 1971 March/April (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Trip correspondence, 1970 Sept. - Oct. (Walker), 1970 September - October (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Trip correspondence, 1970 April/May (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Trip correspondence, 1970 April/May (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trip correspondence, 1970 Jan. - Feb. (Walker), 1970 January - February (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Trip correspondence, 1972 Nov. - Dec. (Walker), 1972 November - December (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Trip correspondence, 1972 Feb. - Mar. (Walker), 1972 February - March (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Trip correspondence, 1972 Summer (Walker) (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Information Bulletin, Stanford Overseas Campuses (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Overseas Campuses, Directors' Conference, Minutes, 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part I, Introduction (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part II, Freshman Attitudes (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part II, Appendix B (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part III, Freshman Curriculum (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part III, Appendix A (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Freshman Year at Stanford, Part IV, Administrative Problems (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Freshman Year Study, Dunsmuir "Retreat," Sept. 16, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Next Decade Study, Final Report, May 1967 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Next Decade Study, Asilomar Conference, Sept. 1966 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Next Decade Study, Humanities and Social Sciences, Minutes and Report (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - [Next Decade Study,] Goals for the Overseas Campuses (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - [Next Decade Study,] Instructional Patterns and Facilities (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - [Next Decade Study,] Goals for Language Instruction in General Studies (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - [Next Decade Study,] Science in General Education (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, General (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, Publicity (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, Report II, Undergraduate Education (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, Report III, University Residences (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, Nov. 1968-Feb. 1970 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, Final Report, Nov. 1, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, Second Interim Report, June 28, 1968 - Sept. 24, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, 1968 February - 1968 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, (Interim Report), 1967 May - 1968 February (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Study of Education at Stanford, IX - Study Abroad, Extra copies of important documents (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - International Studies Committee, general, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - International Studies Committee, general, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - International Studies Committee, area studies, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - International Studies Committee, Center for Research, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - International Studies Committee, Overseas programs, 1967-1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)